<opt>Soil does NOT remain in ball when squeezed
  <desc>Place approximately 25 g soil in palm. Add water dropwise and knead the soil to break down all aggregates. Soil is at the proper consistency when plastic and moldable, like moist putty.  </desc>
  <opt>
    Is too dry
    <desc>The soil sample is too dry.  </desc>
    <opt>
      NO RESULT: Add more water and start again
    </opt>
  </opt>
  <opt>Is too wet
    <desc>The soil sample is too wet.  </desc>
    <opt>
      NO RESULT: Add dry soil and start again
      <desc>NO RESULT: add dry soil to soak up water </desc>
    </opt>
  </opt>
  <opt>NOT too wet nor too dry
    <desc>The soil is NOT too wet nor too dry.  </desc>
    <opt>
      Sand
      <desc>A sand has a loose gritty feel and does not stick together. Individual sand grains can be seen or felt. (VDEPI 2009: AG0058) </desc>
    </opt>
  </opt>
</opt>
<opt>Soil remains in ball when squeezed
  <desc>Place approximately 25 g soil in palm. Add water dropwise and knead the soil to break down all aggregates. Soil is at the proper consistency when plastic and moldable, like moist putty.  </desc>
  <opt>
    TASK: Roll ribbon
    <desc>Rub a ball of soil between thumb and forefinger to make a 'ribbon' </desc>
    <opt>
      Does NOT form a ribbom
      <desc>A 'ribbon' is NOT formed when a ball of soil is rubbed between thumb and forefinger.  </desc>
      <opt>
        Loamy Sand
        <desc>In a loamy sand particles barely stick together and a moulded piece of soil just holds its shape. (VDEPI 2009: AG0058) </desc>
      </opt>
    </opt>
    <opt>Forms ribbon
      <desc>A 'ribbon' is formed when a ball of soil is rubbed between thumb and forefinger.  </desc>
      <opt>
        Medium ribbon (2.5-5cm long)
        <desc>The ribbon formed when a ball of soil is rubbed between thumb and forefinger is between 2.5 and 5cm long.  </desc>
        <opt>
          TASK: Wet soil and rub with forefinger
          <desc>Excessively wet a small pinch of soil in palm and rub with forefinger.  </desc>
          <opt>
            Does NOT feel very gritty
            <desc>The wetted soil does NOT feel very gritty when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
            <opt>
              Feels very smooth
              <desc>The wetted soil feels very smooth when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
              <opt>
                Silty Clay Loam
                <desc>A silty clay loam is like a clay loam but silty as well and smooth to the touch. (VDEPI 2009: AG0058) </desc>
              </opt>
            </opt>
            <opt>Neither very gritty nor very smooth
              <desc>The wetted soil does NOT feel very smooth nor very gritty when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
              <opt>
                Clay Loam
                <desc>More easily moulded into a shape than a loam, a clay loam rolls out to a thin ribbon between the palms while a loam will break-up. When dry a clay loam will form a lump but is not as tough to break as a clay.(VDEPI 2009: AG0058) </desc>
              </opt>
            </opt>
          </opt>
          <opt>Feels very gritty
            <desc>The wetted soil feels very gritty when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
            <opt>
              Sandy Clay Loam
              <desc>A sandy clay loam is like a clay loam but sand grains can be felt (and heard - see Sandy Loam) (VDEPI 2009: AG0058) </desc>
            </opt>
          </opt>
        </opt>
      </opt>
      <opt>Strong ribbon
        <desc>The ribbon formed when a ball of soil is rubbed between thumb and forefinger is strong and over 5cm long.  </desc>
        <opt>
          TASK: Wet soil and rub with forefinger
          <desc>Excessively wet a small pinch of soil in palm and rub with forefinger.  </desc>
          <opt>
            Does NOT feel very gritty
            <desc>The wetted soil does NOT feel very gritty when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
            <opt>
              Feels very smooth
              <desc>The wetted soil feels very smooth when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
              <opt>
                Silty Clay
                <desc>A silty clay is like a clay but smoother. (VDEPI 2009: AG0058) </desc>
              </opt>
            </opt>
            <opt>Neither very gritty nor very smooth
              <desc>The wetted soil does NOT feel very smooth nor very gritty when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
              <opt>
                Clay
                <desc>Clays are tough and can be moulded into shapes when moist. Clays form a long flexible ribbon when rubbed between the palms and the ribbon can often be bent into a U shape without breaking. Clays dry into very hard clods. (VDEPI 2009: AG0058) </desc>
              </opt>
            </opt>
          </opt>
          <opt>Feels very gritty
            <desc>The wetted soil feels very gritty when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
            <opt>
              Sandy Clay
              <desc>A sandy clay is like a clay but sand grains can be felt (and heard - see Sandy Loam). (VDEPI 2009: AG0058) </desc>
            </opt>
          </opt>
        </opt>
      </opt>
      <opt>Weak ribbon (&lt;2.5cm long)
        <desc>The ribbon formed when a ball of soil is rubbed between thumb and forefinger is less than 2.5cm long.  </desc>
        <opt>
          TASK: Wet soil and rub with forefinger
          <desc>Excessively wet a small pinch of soil in palm and rub with forefinger.  </desc>
          <opt>
            Does NOT feel very gritty
            <desc>The wetted soil does NOT feel very gritty when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
            <opt>
              Feels very smooth
              <desc>The wetted soil feels very smooth when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
              <opt>
                Silt Loam
                <desc>A silty loam is like a loam but has a smooth silky feel when a moist sample is pushed between the index finger and thumb. On drying a sample can form a hard lump but this may be broken by hand. (VDEPI 2009: AG0058) </desc>
              </opt>
            </opt>
            <opt>Neither very gritty nor very smooth
              <desc>The wetted soil does NOT feel very smooth nor very gritty when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
              <opt>
                Loam
                <desc>A loam breaks into crumbs but will tend to stick together. Sand grains cannot be felt in a moist sample which when squeezed will retain its shape when handled freely. Loams are usually soft to the feel. (VDEPI 2009: AG0058) </desc>
              </opt>
            </opt>
          </opt>
          <opt>Feels very gritty
            <desc>The wetted soil feels very gritty when rubbed on the palm and with forefinger.  </desc>
            <opt>
              Sandy Loam
              <desc>A sandy loam sticks together more than a loamy sand but can be easily broken. Individual sand grains can be felt and heard if a wet sample is rubbed between the index finger and thumb and held close to the ear. (VDEPI 2009: AG0058) </desc>
            </opt>
          </opt>
        </opt>
      </opt>
    </opt>
  </opt>
</opt>
